Guide to the Darcus Howe Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Darcus Howe Papers,
1965-2008.
Howe, Darcus
12.5 linear ft. (17 boxes; 9 document boxes, 1 half-sized document box; 7 record storage cartons)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1476
7089617
These papers contain correspondence, writings, interview transcripts, court reports and transcripts, printed material, and audio and video tapes regarding the life and work of journalist and activist, Darcus Howe—a British citizen and native of Trinidad. Also in the papers is a small amount of material related to the writer and activist, C L R James.
Biographical Note
Activist, print and television journalist, and Trinidadian native Darcus Howe has resided in London for most of his adult life. Howe, christened Leighton Rhett Radford, was born in Moruga, of Southern Trinidad, on February 26, 1943, one of five siblings. His parents, Cipriani Nathaniel Howe, an Anglican Priest, and Lucille Howe, both taught at the Eckles Village Anglican School, which Howe attended during his primary school years. In 1955 Howe received an "exhibition" or full scholarship to Queen's Royal College, in Port of Spain, one of the oldest secondary schools in Trinidad. He graduated from QRC in 1959 and began work with the Post Office. In 1962, at the age of 19, Howe left for Britain.
In London Howe worked first, as he had in Trinidad, in the Post Office. He also studied law at London's Middle Temple but abandoned the classroom, before completing his degree, for a career in journalism and in activism. Although never called to the English bar, Howe's legal studies paid off handsomely in his many subsequent arrests, trials and brushes with the law. Upon leaving Middle Temple Howe returned briefly to Trinidad where he edited Vanguard, the journal of the Oilfield Workers' Trade Union. By 1970, Howe had returned to London permanently and in 1988 he became a British citizen.
During the early 1970s Howe was active in Britain's Black Panther Movement, but by 1972 his energies were directed to the work of the Race Today Collective. He edited the Collective's publication, Race Today with Leila Hassan. Members and affiliates of the Collective, which reflected both the geographic breadth of Britain's former colonial reach and the depth of diversity then in London included: Indian-born British writer Farukh Dhondy; Zanzibarian co-editor of Race Today Leila Hassan; Jamaican dub—or reggae—poet Linton Kwesi Johnson; Gernada native, and the first black education director for the London borough of Hackney—or for any borough, Gus John; as well as Howe. Over the years the Collective expanded its editorial operation, publishing pamphlets and books, along with Race Today, and co-sponsoring the International Book Fair of Radical, Black and Third World Books.
Notting Hill's Mangrove Cafe, established in 1968 by Frank Critchlow, served as something of a community center, a home base for West Indian political radicals and as a lightening rod for the London police who raided the cafe with some regularity. After one too many raids, demonstrators marched on the Notting Hill Police Station in August of 1970 protesting "police attacks on black people's home and the places [they] frequent." Howe, Barbara Beese, Rupert Boyce, Frank Critchlow, Rhodan Gordon, Anthony Inniss, Rothwell Kentish, Althea Lecointe and Godfrey Millette—the Mangrove 9—were arrested during the demonstartion and charged with "riot and affray," among other charges. Howe and Lecointe chose to defend themselves. It was not Howe's first arrest and it would not be his last trial, but it was his first attempt to defend himself in court. Following a 55 days-long trial in Old Bailey, Howe was aquitted on all counts.
Howe's journalism ventures expanded into television in the 1980s. From 1985 to 1991, Howe, and Tariq Ali, co-produced documentaries and interviewed prominent political figures around the globe for the Bandung File, which aired on Britain's Channel Four Television. The Devil's Advocate, with Howe as a host, followed the demise of the Bandung File. Later documentaries by Howe included White Tribe, Who You Calling a Nigger?, Son of Mine, and in 2009 What's Killing Darcus Howe?, an attempt to raise awareness, particularly among black men, of prostate cancer.
In print Howe contributed regularly to The Guardian, The Times, The Yorkshire Post and The New Statesman; by the 1990s Howe wrote a weekly column, "Thinking Aloud" for The Sunday Mirror.
Howe is a first cousin, once removed, of C L R James. Their common ancestor, Joshua Rudder, was Howe's great-grandfather, and James' grandfather. Rudder's children included sisters Florrie—Howe's maternal grandmother—and Bessie—James' mother—thereby rendering Lucille (Darcus's mother) and James first cousins. In the 1980s and until his death in 1989, CLR James lived in the rooms of the Race Today Collective.
Howe has seven children. In 1989 Howe and his long-time lover, Leila Hassan, were married. Howe was diagnosed with prostate cancer in 2007, but is currently in remission.
Scope and Content
The Darcus Howe Papers include correspondence, writings, interview transcripts, court reports and transcripts, printed material, audio and video tapes regarding Howe and his work as an activist and a journalist. The small amount of material here related to C L R James consists primarily of tributes, events and photographs honoring or memorializing James.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series:
Series I. CLR James, 1974-1996
Series II. Darcus Howe, 1965-2008
Subseries II.1. General, 1965, 1973-2008
Subseries II.2. Activism and Politics, 1969-2002
Subseries II.3. Writings, Journalism and Media, 1970s-1990s
Subseries II.4 Printed Material, 1970s-1990s
Series III. Audio/Video, circa 1970s-1990s
Subjects
Black Panther Movement.; Channel 4 TV (Great Britain).; Race Today Collective.; Howe, Darcus.; James, C. L. R. (Cyril Lionel Robert), 1901-1989.; London (England)--Race relations.; West Indians--Great Britain.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Purchase 2009 January
Related Material at Columbia
C.L.R. James Papers Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Anna Grimshaw Papers Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Constance Webb Papers Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Series I: CLR James, 1974-1996
  A small amount of correspondence to and from James is contained here along with a series of lectures, transcribed, that James delivered at an event celebrating his 80th birthday; material related to his death and funeral, including photographs of the funeral and procession; lectures and other items from exhibits, tributes and festivals honoring James; and correspondence and documents—including architectural drawings—regarding the effort to establish a C L R James Foundation/Institute in London.
  - Correspondence
    - 1974, 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Divorce, Regarding, 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - James-Howe, 1976-1983, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Death of
    - Condolences, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence regarding, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Estate, 1989-1990, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Funeral, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Funeral--Photos, 1989 (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 8 to 9)
  - Finances, 1987, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Interviews--Regarding, 1981, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, Circa 1980s (Box 11, Folder 1 to 4)
  - Printed Material, 1986, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Printed Material--Clippings, 1984-1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Programs and Events, 1981-1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Trinity Cross, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Writings
    - 1981, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Lectures, Circa 1970s (Photocopies) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Lectures--80th Birthday--Transcripts, Circa 1981 (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 1 to 2)
    - "Walter Rodney and the Question of Power", 1983, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Tomorrow and Today: A Vision"--Annotated, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Exhibit--Lectures by
    - Archer, John, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Boggs, Grace Lee and Martin Glaberman, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Harris, Wilson, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Hector, Tim, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Festival, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Festival--Correspondence, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Foundation/Institute
    - General, 1983-1994 (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 11 to 12)
    - Correspondence, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Drawings and Plans, 1993, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Expenses, 1993-1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Meetings, 1989, 1992-1996 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Studies of, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Tributes to, circa 1989-1990 (2 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 5 to 6)
- Series II: Darcus Howe, 1965-2008
  This series includes correspondence to and from Howe; writings and interview transcripts; court reports, transcripts of cross examinations and other trial-related material; printed material and photographs related to Darcus Howe's life, work and activism.
  - Subseries II.1: General, 1965, 1973-2008
    Correspondence, address books and an agenda, material related to several funerals, photographs, and a few subject files comprise this small subseries.
    - Correspondence
      - 1973-2008 (4 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 7 to 10)
      - "Personal," 1977-1993, Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - "Speaking Engagements", 1979-2004 (4 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 12 to 15)
    - Personal
      - General, 1988-1999, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Address Books, Undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Daily Agenda, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Funerals and Memorial Services, 1983-1997 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Howe, Cipriani--Death of, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Breeze, Jean Binta, 1988- circa 1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Carnival, 1977-2003 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Cricket--Research, 1965, 1983, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Jamaican Theater--Interview with Honor Ford Smith, Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Photograph--Darcus Howe--Imperial Typewriters Strike, circa 1970s (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Photos, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Subseries II.2: Activism and Politics, 1969-2002
    Found here are court reports, transcripts of cross examinations and other material related to the Mangrove 9 Trial; correspondence and documents regarding the Race Today Collective; and statements, printed material and other items related primarily to the Black Panthers Movement in Britain and the United States invasion of Grenada in 1983.
    - Black Panther Movement
      - General, 1970-1971, Undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Cadogan, David Oscar, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - "Freedom News", 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - "National and International News Bulletin", 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Writings--Drafts, Circa 1970s (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Writings--Drafts, and Notes, Circa 1970s (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Black Politics--United Kingdom, circa 1980s (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Grenada
      - Addresses and Statements, 1983, Undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Committee Meetings, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Diary--Christina in Cariacou, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Diary--Gus John, circa 1983 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Printed Material, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Guyana Bauxite Workers--Printed Material, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Hector, Tim--Printed Material, 1987, 1989, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Howe, Darcus Action Committee
      - General, 1977-1980 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Financial, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Statements, 1978, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - International Book Fair of Radical, Black and Third World Books--Printed Material, 1985-1989 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Mangrove 9 Trial
      - General, circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence, 1971-1973, 1980, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Community Association, 1976-1986, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Court Reports, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Printed Material, 1971-1973 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Cross Examinations, 1971 (6 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 7 to 12)
      - Evidence of P C Pulley--Volume 2, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - Statements, Index of, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Statements of Witnesses, 1970 (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 2 to 3)
    - New Beginning Movement, 1971-1978 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Police--General, 1973, 1980-1983 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Police--Trinidad and Tobago--Complaint Against, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Race Today Collective
      - Correspondence
        - 1984-1990, Undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
        - A-T, 1976-1988, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 8 to 9)
        - "Europe"--1980-1985 Undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
        - Permissions, 1989-1993 (Box 7, Folder 11)
        - References, 1976-1978, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 12)
        - Spencer, Marva, 1989 October-1990 January (Box 7, Folder 13)
        - "West Indies", 1978-1988, Undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - Bradford Black Conference, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Community Relations, 1972-1973, Undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Dick, Patricia, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Reorganization of
        - General, 1988-1991 (Box 8, Folder 4)
        - Dissolution, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 5)
        - Drafts, Circa 1988-1991 (Box 8, Folder 6)
        - Drafts and Notes, Circa 1988-1991 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Rules, Circa 1978 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Seminar--Black Aesthetic, Undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - United States Meeting--Transcript, Circa 1984 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - West Indies
      - General, 1984, Undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - Oilfield Workers Trade Union, 1984-1988 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Subseries II.3: Writings, Journalism and Media, 1970s-1990s
    Transcripts of interviews by and of Howe; addresses, drafts and writings including materials of From Bobby to Babylon from draft to galley stage; and a few television production related items are included in this subseries.
    - Addresses
      - Caribbean in Crisis--International Book Fair, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 13)
      - Eulogy--for William Johnson, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 14)
      - Speeches, 1978, 1988 (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 15 to 16)
      - Tribute to CLR James, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - "Black Sections in the Labor Party", 1985 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Bobby to Babylon
      - Drafts, circa 1980s (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 19 to 20)
      - Galleys, circa 1980s (Box 8, Folder 21)
      - Printed, 1980-1982, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Book Proposal--England, My England, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Drafts--General, 1990, 1992, Undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Drafts--Fragments, Undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Drafts--Race Today, Undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Notebooks, 1991, Undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - "Thinking Aloud"--Correspondence, 1989-1992, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - "Thinking Aloud"--Clippings, 1991-1993 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Interview of Darcus Howe--Transcripts, 1992-1993, Undated (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 9 to 10)
    - Interviews by Darcus Howe--Transcripts
      - Ali, Tariq, 1985-1986 (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Jackson, Jesse, Undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - MacDonald, Ian, Undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
      - Mugabe, Robert, circa 1990s (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Television
      - Devil's Advocate, 1992-1993 (Box 9, Folder 15)
      - Playground Discussion--Teenage Gang Rape, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 16)
      - White Tribe, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Subseries II.4: Printed Material, 1970s-1990s
    Contained here are journals, bulletins and pamphlets published by the Race Today Collective; and clippings, flyers, announcements and pamphlets from other organizations.
    - General, Circa 1980s, Undated (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - General--Pamphlets, 1972-1987 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Announcements and Flyers, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Clippings--Darcus Howe, 1976-1999, Undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - New Beginning Movement--"History of the Working-Class in the 20th Century--Trinidad and Tobago by Bukka Rennie," 1974 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - New Beginning Movement--"Trinidad Revolution, the Present Stage of", 1974 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Oilfield Workers Trade Union--Forum--Political Commentary by Darcus Howe, Tim Hector and Biodun Jeyifo, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Race Today Collective
      - The Arrivants--A Pictorial Essay on Blacks in Britain, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - "Black Women in Britain", 1975 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Bulletins, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - C L R James-- A History of Negro Revolt--3rd Edition, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - Pamphlets, 1974-1985 (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - Poems of Michael Smith, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 10)
      - Race Today, 1974-1982 (8 Bound Volumes) (Box 10, Folder 11 to 18)
      - Race Today, 1988 January/February (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Teachers Action, circa 1970s (Box 10, Folder 20)
- Series III. Audio/ Video--circa 1970s-1990s
  This, the largest series of the collection, includes audio and video cassette tapes of interviews with C L R James and others; conferences; Race Today Collective meetings; and Bandung and other television productions.
  - Audio Cassette Tapes, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 12)
  - Video Cassette Tapes, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 13-17)